<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Science on Phil Chapman&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/categories/data-science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data Science on Phil Chapman&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/data-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Dockerizing your R analysis</title>
      <link>/post/2019/02/02/dockerizing-your-r-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2019/02/02/dockerizing-your-r-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This post is the first in a series of blog posts about getting the things that we do with R out into the world beyond the normal R ecosystem. I&amp;rsquo;ll be talking about exploratory analyses, shiny apps, models, serverless functions, R packages, and Docker. A lot about Docker.
Why should you care? Why should you care about this? Well, if as a R user you can only really collaborate with other R users, you&amp;rsquo;re limiting yourself as a data scientist.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Last day as a civil servant</title>
      <link>/post/2018/11/27/last-day-civil-servant/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/11/27/last-day-civil-servant/</guid>
      <description>Moving from bioinformatics to data science Almost exactly a year after contemplating my last day as a bioinformatician, I am now contemplating my last day as a data scientist in the Department for Work and Pensions, part of the UK civil service.
As I&amp;rsquo;ve blogged about previously, bioinformatics experience is highly relevant in the data science job market, and I&amp;rsquo;ve also discovered how important the ‘science’ bit of data science is.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible data science environments with Docker</title>
      <link>/post/2018/05/26/reproducible-data-science-environments-with-docker/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/05/26/reproducible-data-science-environments-with-docker/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Since starting at DWP Digital, I&amp;rsquo;ve spent quite a bit of time working with some colleagues developing our analysis environments. We need to be able to control and adapt our environments quite rapidly so that we can use the latest and greatest tools, but we also need these environments to be robust and reproducible and to be deployed in a variety of hosting contexts including laptops and our secure internal environment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why bioinformaticians should consider themselves data scientists</title>
      <link>/post/2018/03/03/why-bioinformaticians-should-consider-themselves-data-scientists/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018/03/03/why-bioinformaticians-should-consider-themselves-data-scientists/</guid>
      <description>My background I&amp;rsquo;ve been a bioinformatician for most of the 20 years since I graduated, but now I&amp;rsquo;m a data scientist working for the Civil Service. In this post I&amp;rsquo;m going to explain why I made this change, and why I think all bioinformaticians should think of themselves as data scientists with a specialism in biology, rather than as a biologist with a specialism in computational science.
I started my career at AstraZeneca working in a genetics and sequencing lab, looking for variations in genes that might explain differential response to drugs.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>